日本列島の最北端にある寒冷地帯
This land, situated in a cold region in the northernmost part of Japan, formerly known as the country of Ezo,
かつて蝦夷の国と呼ばれたこの土地は
その複雑な地形と厳しい自然環境故に 人を寄せ付けず
still has much primitive wildlife due to its complex geography and harsh natural environment that are unsuitable for living in.
いまだ原始の自然や動植物が残っております
生きとし生けるものの
All living things in the Ezo region participate in a merciless battle of life and death every day.
生死を懸けた過酷な闘いが
日々繰り広げられる蝦夷地
寒い寒い寒い寒い
Cold cold cold cold!
I'll die I'll die! I'm gonna die!
死ぬ死ぬ死ぬ死んでしまうー
そんな厳しい蝦夷地の中でも
This particular region, known even in Ezo to have particularly harsh snowstorms,
極度の豪雪地帯と恐れられる
and which is also designated a first class disaster area — Mount Odori,
壱級災害指定地域 絶対凍土の踊山に
奇策士とがめと鑢七花が生死を懸けて登っていたのでございます
is where the strategian Togame and the 7th generation Kyotouryuu head Yasuri Shichika find themselves climbing for their lives.
Dammit, piling up on my head's like this...
勝手に人の頭の上に積もってゆくとは
Annoying snow!
いまいましい雪め
Ow, ouch!
痛っ痛えよ
It's your own fault for not dodging!
そなたがよけないのがいけないのだ
You say that...
しかしすげえな
But this really is amazing.
これが蝦夷の雪っ子ってやつか
So this is what they call Ezo snow?
雪もすげえけど ホントにすげえのは風なんだな
The snow is quite something, but what's really amazing is the wind.
風がすごいから膝までしか積もらない
The wind is so strong that snow only builds up to knee height.
It's like a constant avalanche.
常に雪崩が起きてるみたいなもんだ
Don't describe it like that!
そんな描写などするな
心まで寒くなってゆくではないか
You'll make me feel even colder!
We aren't even halfway up the mountain, you know.
だってよ まだ山の中腹までも来てないんだぜ
I can't even imagine what it's going to be like at the peak.
頂上なんてどんなことになってんだか 想像もつかないよ
しかもそこに住んでんだろ
And they live up there, right?
That "Itezora" clan, was it?
凍空一族だっけ
いったいどんなやつらなんだ とがめ
What kind of people are they anyway, Togame?
うっ きっと雪だるまみたいなやからではないかな
They probably look like snowmen.
Or they could be covered in thick fur and look like the abominable snowman.
いや 全身毛むくじゃらの雪男みたいな種族とか
Well, no doubt they're resistant to the cold, anyway.
まあ 寒さに強いということだけは間違いないぞ
"No doubt"... you don't actually know?
「間違いないぞ」って とがめ知らねえのかよ
Nope. Not at all.
知らん まったく知らん
And while we're on the topic, I haven't heard a single thing about Soutou Kanazuchi, either.
ついでを言うなら 「双刀·鎚」のことも噂一つ聞かん
Soutou Kanazuchi
Hammer,
The Pair
Soutou is written "pair of swords", so it could be a set of two swords.
双つの刀と書いて「双刀」という名故に
二本一組かもしれぬしな
まあ 凍空一族の先祖は出雲のだいだら法師らしいぞ
I do know that the Itezora clan's ancestors were apparently the giants of Izumo.
そいつは使える情報だな
Well that's useful to know...
...not.
って とがめそんなに何も知らなくて
Togame, how are you going to make any plans with such little information?
どうやって策を練るんだよ
Does "Strategian" mean "someone who doesn't make plans"?
奇策士ってのは策を練らねえやつのことなのか
Moron! I would never make plans!
ほざけ
わたしは策など練らん わたしが練るのは奇策だ
What I come up with are schemes!
By "schemes", do you mean "guessing as you go along"?
奇策ってのは行き当たりばったりってことなのか
Wh-What!
なっ 何この ちぇっちぇるれお
Why you!
Ch-Cherirurero!
寒いと巻き舌になるんだなとがめは
I see you get your tongue in a twist when it's cold.
無駄口をたたく暇があったらさっさと登るぞ
If you've got the time to waste talking, hurry up and climb!
If you don't hurry up, I'm going to turn into a snowman!
早くしないとこちらが雪だるまになってしまうわ
Soutou
Kanazuchi
Owari
castle
grounds
Though I must say,
Princess
Hitei's
palace
それにしても
that woman really is impossible to read, going straight from Satsuma to Ezo like that...
薩摩から蝦夷に一っ飛びとは
相変わらず読めない女だわね
She must have heard about my return to power by now.
そろそろ わたしが尾張で復権したと聞いても
Is this a display of confidence on her part?
おかしくないはずなのに余裕のつもりかしら
あんたはどう思う 右衛門左衛門
What do you think, Emon Zaemon?
何とも言えません
I really couldn't say.
Boring!
つまらない
What a boring man you are.
とに面白くない男ね
Have you forgotten who went to the effort of putting a mask over that face of yours,
闇より暗いあんたの暗黒顔に仮面を着け
darker than darkness itself, and bothered to write "unconcealed" on it?
わざわざ「不忍」の２文字をあげたのは誰か忘れたの
That would be my princess—
それは姫さまが
Shut up!
ああ うざっ
I'm not looking for an answer.
答えなんて聞いてないわよ 答えなんて
I don't need an answer!
I deny it.
否定する
I deny the day I employed you!
あんたを雇った日をわたしは否定するわ
蝦夷といえば絶対凍土
If they're in Ezo, they'll be heading towards the frozen land designated as a first class disaster region, Mt. Odori.
壱級災害指定地域の踊山
あそこには凍空一族が持つ「双刀·鎚」があるはず
That would be where the sword they seek, Soutou Kanazuchi, is held by the Itezora clan.
２人はその鎚の収集のために向かったかと
I thought as much.
そんなことだろうと思ったのよ
But does that woman really think it will be easy?
それにしてもあの女 簡単にいくと思っているのかしら
What do you mean?
と言いますと
Do you know why Mt. Odori was designated a disaster region?
踊山が災害地域に指定された本当の理由知ってる
Wasn't it because it harbors the harshest snowstorms in Japan?
日本最大の豪雪地帯だからではないのですか
きっとあの不愉快な女もそう思っているわよね
That unpleasant woman probably thinks the same.
It was designated as such not because of the mountain itself, but because of the inhabitants of the mountain —
災害指定はね踊山にではなく
古来より踊山に住まう者ども
the owners of Kanazuchi — the Itezora clan, who have lived there since the distant past.
鎚の所有者 凍空一族に対して発せられたものなのよ
This sounds like it'll get interesting.
面白くなりそうね
She can go ahead and keep flirting with that Kyotouryuu until she realizes what the real situation is.
事情が分かるまでせいぜいあの虚刀流といちゃついていればいいわ
S-Shichika...
し 七花
If I die...
わたしが死んだらあ
Huh?
わたしが死んだら
If I die, please make all of Japan adopt "cheerio" as a catchphrase that means a shout to fire you up...
そなた一人で
「ちぇりお」を気合を入れるための掛け声として日本中にはやらせてくれ
Wha.. what are you saying?
なっ 何言ってんだよ しっかりしろよとがめ
Pull yourself together, Togame!
I can't take it anymore...
わたしはもう無理だ
おっおい
H-Hey!
どうやらここまでのようだ
This looks like the end for me...
So please, Shichika...
だから 七花
If nothing else, please make "cheerio"...
「ちぇりお」のことだけはどうか
That's impossible!
無茶言うなよ
There's no way I could make "cheerio" catch on with the wrong meaning!
「ちぇりお」を間違った意味ではやらせるなんて
そんなの俺一人じゃできないよ
You can do it...
そなたならできる そなたはわたしが選んだ刀だ
You are the sword I chose.
Impossible!
無理だ とがめがいてくれなきゃ
I can't do anything without you!
俺なんか何にもできないよ
What are you saying?
何を言う
I've taught you everything I can already.
この半年でわたしはそなたに教えられるかぎりのことは教えた
もうわたしの奇策なぞ必要ないさ
You don't need my schemes anymore.
What?
なっとがめにはまだやらなくちゃいけないことがあるだろう
You still have things to do!
During this journey with you, I've realized for the first time...
そなたと旅をして
わたしは初めて気付かされた
わたしのやってきたことは本当は何の意味もないのではないかと
Everything I've done so far is meaningless...
True happiness is finding the one you love and becoming a mother,
本当の幸せとは
誰かと共に新たな命をはぐくむこと
前に向かって共に歩むことだと
and then living your life out with them.
そんなことにさえ わたしはこれまで気付かなかったのだ
In the past, I hadn't even considered such a thing.
とがめ それに気付くのはちょっとまだ早いんじゃ
Isn't it a bit too early for you to be thinking about that?
I've walked this path for 20 years...
２０年間孤独にこの道を歩んできたわたしだが
but in the mere half year since we met, you've taught me how a human should live life.
出会ってたかが半年のそなたに教えられた
人はどう生きるべきなのかと
No, I really haven't done anything to change your outlook on life yet...
いや 俺はまだあんたの人生観を変えるようなことはしてねえよ
何か俺の体変だ
My body seems kind of strange...
何すんじゃ
What are you doing?!
Shichika?
七花
Shichirin?
しちりん
Hey, Shichika!
七花 おいああっ
Shichika!
七花 ああっ
I thought you'd died!
死んだかと思ったぞ どうしたのだ
What's wrong?
My limbs won't move like I want them to...
てっ 手足が思うように動かない
凍傷だ たわけが
You've got frostbite, you idiot!
If you're cold, why didn't you say so?
寒いなら寒いと言わんか
I didn't think you were just putting up a strong face!
やせ我慢しておったとは思わんかったわ
Well no, I'm not cold, but I'm kind of losing control of my body.
いや 寒くはないんだけど
体がだんだん言うことを聞かなくなって
Idiot!
このバカ 鈍いにも程があるわ
How dull can you get?
ああ これが寒いって感覚なのか
So this is what "cold" feels like...
No, don't go to sleep!
駄目だ 寝るな
If you sleep, you'll die!
寝たら死ぬぞ
Shichika!
七花
Open your eyes!
目を開けろ 開けてくれああっ
Open your—
Wake up!
起きろ
目を開けてくれ 頼む
Please, wake up!
Shichika...
七花
どうしよう
What do I do...
What should I do?
どうすれば
What should I do...
Um...
あの
大丈夫ですか
Are you okay?
行きますよ
Here we go!
At the exact moment when the strategian Togame and Shichika were saved by Itezora Konayuki,
奇策士とがめと七花が
凍空こなゆきに助けられましたまさにそのとき
the 12 heads of the specialist assassins, the Maniwa Corps, were gathered in the Maniwa village.
暗殺専門の真庭忍軍十二頭領全員が
真庭の里に集まっておりました
Though, having said 12 heads, there are only 6 here.
十二頭領といいましても
集まっているのは６人のみ
Maniwa "Phoenix God" Houou,
「神の鳳凰」こと真庭鳳凰
「長寿の海亀」こと真庭海亀
Maniwa "Sea Turtle the Long-lived" Umigame,
Maniwa "Mandarin Duck the Rewind" Oshidori,
「巻き戻しの鴛鴦」こと真庭鴛鴦
Maniwa "Otter the Investigator" Kawauso,
「読み調べの川獺」こと真庭川獺
Maniwa "Penguin the Proliferate" Pengin,
「増殖の人鳥」こと真庭人鳥
and the shapeless Maniwa "Rabid Dog the Infectious" Kyouken.
そして姿なき「伝染の狂犬」こと真庭狂犬
Indeed, the Maniwa Corps have been halved in number this past half year.
そう
真庭忍軍はここ半年ほどで
その数を半数にまで減らされていたのでございます
The effective leader of the Maniwa Corps, Maniwa Houou, was in the middle of his report to the other 5 heads,
その危機的状況を受け
真庭忍軍の実質的な頭 真庭鳳凰は
先月薩摩にて
and was explaining how the crisis had driven him to form an alliance with the strategian Togame in Satsuma.
奇策士とがめと同盟を締結したことを
５人の頭領たちに報告していたのでございます
And thus, we must all move together as a unit from now on.
故に ここから先は皆が一丸となって動く必要がある
It is unavoidable, if it's true that the Insect squad really has been exterminated.
あの虫組３人が全滅したとなれば それも致し方あるまい
I know you were on close terms with the Insect squad's Chouchou.
お主と虫組の蝶々はいい仲だったのだろう
ならば こたびの同盟はお主にとっては不本意なものとなろうな
I'm guessing this alliance goes against your wishes.
No, Chouchou and I merely serve the Maniwa Corps.
いいえ わたしも蝶々も真庭忍軍の末席を汚す者
あだ討ちや報復のために動こうとは思いません
I would never consider acting on my own for revenge.
Right?
だな
As far as revenge goes, personally I have a burning desire to avenge that Koumori idiot.
あだ討ちっつーなら
俺は蝙蝠のバカのあだ討ちをしたくてしたくてしょうがねえよ
あいつは俺の親友だったんだ
He was my friend...
けどよそこはぐっとこらえるのが忍びの心意気ってもんだろ
but bearing this pain is what shinobi must do.
If we can achieve our goal at the end of it all,
it will make up for their losses a little.
最終的にわれらが目的を達成すれば 少しは報われるだろう
To do that, we must start collecting swords as quickly as possible.
それにはわしらが一刻も早く刀を集めることだ
Right.
だな しかもとがめちゃんたちと衝突せずにだろ
While avoiding conflict with Togame-chan too, right?
The three swords I told the strategian about are in Shireizan, Tendou, and Edo,
われが奇策士に教えた３本の刀の所在はそれぞれ
死霊山 天童 江戸であるが
but for some reason they headed for Ezo.
奇策士らはなぜか蝦夷に向かった
Um... i-isn't Ezo where S-S-Soutou Kanazuchi is?
あっ あの えっ蝦夷ならそっ「双刀·鎚」があるはずです
Your information gathering abilities are as impressive as ever.
相変わらずお主の情報収集力はさすがだな
蝙蝠亡き今刀集めの成否はお主と川獺にかかっているといってもよさそうだ
With Koumori no longer with us, it's no exaggeration to say that the success of our sword collection plan rests on you.
ではわたしたちはその４本を除いた刀を探せばよいということですね
Then we should search for the swords in locations other than those four.
Correct.
そういうことだ
U-Um...
あっ あの あの あの
Um, um, um!
What is it, Pengin?
どうした人鳥
A-About that point, or rather, about the swords' locations...
さっ先ほどの話の続きといいますか
刀の所在なんですが 死霊山
Shireizan...
Shireizan?
死霊山
There's n-no longer a sword in Shireizan.
死霊山にはもう刀はないです
Or r-rather, Shireizan itself...
というか死霊山自体が
I-I don't know wh-who it was, but someone laid waste to Shireizan in just half an hour and took the sword.
だっ 誰の仕業かまだ分かっていませんが
その者は死霊山をわずか半時で壊滅に追い込み
刀を奪っていったらしいです
What on earth...
何と そんな化け物が存在するとなると
If such a monster exists, I think you'll have to move for us, Kyouken.
お主に動いてもらうしかなさそうだな 狂犬
Kyouken?
狂犬
Kawauso, how long was Kyouken here?
川獺 狂犬はいつまでここにいた
勘弁してくれよ
Give me a break...
When she moves seriously, even another member of the Beast Squad like me can't follow her movements.
今のあいつが本気で動いたら
同じ獣組の俺にだって捕らえきれねえよ
鳳凰さんが蝦夷うんぬん言ってたときはまだいたように思うがね
Though, I had a feeling she was still around when you were talking about that Ezo stuff.
まずいな
This is bad.
That means she's gone after the strategian.
ということは奇策士を追ったか
That Kyouken is particularly emotional, after all.
狂犬のやつは人一倍情に厚いからな
I doubt we'll be able to stop her.
わしらに止めることはできぬだろう
だな
Right?
狂犬が動いたってことは
If Kyouken is on the move...
The alliance will fall apart just one month after it was formed.
同盟は締結してから１カ月持たずに崩壊する
Now that it's come to this, we have no choice.
こうなったらしかたがない
ゆくぞ 川獺
Let's go, Kawauso.
As you wish.
望むところよ
Strategian-chan, Kyotouryuu-chan...
奇策士ちゃん 虚刀流ちゃん
わたしをこれだけ怒らせたのは あんたたちが初めてよ
You are the first people to make me this angry.
I'll never forgive you!
許さないわ
I will avenge my friends!
仲間の敵はわたしが討つ
Got it?
いいこと わたしが踊山に着くまで凍死するんじゃないわよ
You'd better not freeze to death before I get to Mt. Odori!
You're an amazingly powerful girl.
お前すげえ力持ちなんだな
You carried me and Togame through this blizzard, right?
この猛吹雪の中
俺ととがめ担いできたんだろ
そんなちみっちゃい体でよ
And with that tiny body of yours too...
そうでないと こんな山で暮らしてられないですからね
I wouldn't be able to live on this kind of  mountain otherwise!
You're pretty amazing too!
お兄ちゃんこそすごいですよ
You climbed halfway up this mountain with a person on your back.
人間１人背負ってこの山の半分まで登ってくるなんて
You have a lot of guts for an land dweller!
地表人としてはなかなかの根性です
A land dweller?
地表人
お兄ちゃんお姉ちゃん お名前教えてもらっていいですか
Onii-chan and Onee-chan, would you tell me your names?
Oh, excuse me.
これは失礼した
わたしは尾張幕府直轄預奉所軍所総監督
Army general director in support of critical tasks under direct control of Yanari Shogun of the Owari Shogunate, Togame the Strategian.
奇策士とがめだ
俺は虚刀流七代目当主鑢七花
I'm the 7th generation Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Shichika.
Togame Onee-chan and Shichika Onii-chan?
とがめお姉ちゃんと七花お兄ちゃんですね
I'm Itezora Konayuki, 11 years old.
うちっちは 凍空こなゆき １１歳です
よろしくです
Nice to meet you!
Itezora...
凍空 なるほど
I see.
ここでそなたと会ったのも何かの縁だなうん
Meeting you here must be a fate.
わたしたちはそなたら一族に用があってここまで来たのだ
We actually came all the way here because we have some business with your clan.
Really? How surprising!
そうなんですか
うちっちびっくり
I'm sorry to ask this right after you saved us, but could you guide us to the Itezora clan's village in the morning?
助けてもらっておいてすまないが
明朝になったら凍空一族の村まで案内してくれまいか
Um, well...
ええとですね 非常に言いづらいんですが
This is very hard to say, but the Itezora village was wiped out in an avalanche just last month.
凍空の村はつい先日起きた雪崩で全滅しちゃったんですよ
Wiped out?
全滅
Yes...
はい
生き残ったのはうちっち１人だけです
I'm the only survivor.
What do we do about our sword gathering now?
じゃ どうすんだよ 刀集め
Sword gathering?
刀集め それって何ですか
What's that?
もしかして うちっちらが
Might we have a sword which Togame Onee-chan and Shichika Onii-chan are looking for?
とがめお姉ちゃんと七花お兄ちゃんが集めてる刀持ってるんですか
Yeah...
四季崎記紀の作りし完成形変体刀十二本が一本
Your clan owns Soutou Kanazuchi, one of the 12 Perfected Deviant Blades which Shikizaki Kiki forged.
「双刀·鎚」をそなた一族が持っておる
Have you heard of it?
聞いたことがあるか
ああ　鎚
Oh, Kanazuchi!
You know about it?
知っておるのか
Not at all!
全然
ごめんなさい うちっち見てのとおり子供ですからね
Sorry, as you can see, I'm just a child.
一族にかかわる秘密とか　大事な話は聞かせてもらえないんですよ
They didn't tell me about important matters or clan secrets.
Then was there anyone in the clan who used a sword?
では　一族の中に刀を使う剣士はいなかったか
うちっちら狩りにしろ料理にしろ工事にしろ
Well, we don't really use swords, whether we're hunting, cooking, or building.
あんまり刃物は使いませんからね
Oh!
Come to think of it, the mayor's eldest son...
そういえば村長の家の長男さんが
What about him?
が どうした
Are you okay?
大丈夫か
大丈夫だ
I'm fine.
それより 村長の家の長男がどうした
More importantly, what was that about the mayor's eldest son?
狩りに使ってるとかいう話を聞いたことがあります
I heard he used a sword when he was hunting.
うちっちはその刀見たことがありませんし
But I haven't seen it, and I don't know if it's Kanazuchi...
その刀が鎚なのかどうかは分かりませんが
どう思う七花
What do you think, Shichika?
No idea.
分からん
俺の共感覚に期待してるんなら　無謀だぜ
If you're placing your hopes on my 6th sense, you're out of luck.
あれは気のせいかもしれないくらい微妙な感覚なんだ
It's such a faint sensation that I might just be imagining it.
Then our only hope is to dig up the area around the mayor's house.
では　村長の家のあった辺りを掘り起こしてみるしかないか
But the village was buried in an avalanche, right?
でも　雪崩で村は埋もれたんだろ
Do you even have any idea where it would have been?
どこにその家があるかなんて検討つくのか
そうであったな
Good point...
If that's the case, how I go out for a bit to fetch it?
何でしたらちょっと行って うちっちが取ってきてあげましょうか
"Go out for a bit"?
ちょっと行ってって
I lived in the village for 10 years, so I have a good idea where it would be.
１０年間住んだ村ですからそれなりに当てはつきます
But there's a vicious snowstorm outside...
しかし外は猛吹雪だぞ
The amount of snow falling makes no difference to us.
うちっちらにとって雪の強弱なんて関係ありませんよ
The snow is a part of us.
雪は体の一部ですし
Whoops, I said "us", but I'm the only one left now.
うちっちらっていっても　もううちっちしか残ってないですけど
じゃあちょっと行って取ってきますから
I'll just go get it then!
ここで待っててくださいね
Please wait here.
取ってくるって　じゃあくれるのかな
"Just go get it"...
Will she just give it to us if it's really Kanazuchi?
その刀が鎚だったら
分からん
I don't know.
鎚が凍空一族にとってどのような刀だったのか定かでないが
It's not clear what meaning Kanazuchi had to the Itezora clan, but it doesn't seem like that girl has any attachment to it.
少なくともあの娘は何の思い入れも持っておらぬようだな
となると　交渉のみ
And that means we may be able to collect this sword with only negotiations, and no battle.
戦闘なしで刀の収集ができるのかもしれぬ
I wonder if Konayuki is being kind to us because she feels lonely after losing everything...
こなゆきが俺たちに親切なのは
全てを失って寂しいから　なのかな
何だよ
What?
そなたが他人の痛みを寂しいという感情をおもんばかるなんてな
I just thought it's strange for you to recognize someone else's pain as "loneliness".
それって褒めてんのか
Is that meant to be a compliment?
Yes, but at the same time I'm concerned.
うむ
同時に案じておる
Concerned?
案じる　何を
About what?
戦えるか
Could you fight?
Yeah, my legs and arms are fine now.
ああ　腕と脚ならもう大丈夫だ
That's not what I mean.
そういうことではない
こなゆきと戦えるかと聞いたのだ
I'm asking if you could fight Konayuki.
A child for an opponent would be easy.
子供が相手なら楽だろ
I see.
そうか　それならいいんだ
That's fine, then.
But to think their village was destroyed by an avalanche after living here hundreds of years...
けどよ　何百年も前からこの山に住んでるのに
雪崩で村がなくなるなんてそんなことあるんだな
I guess even these things happen.
凍空一族の里って山頂にあるんだろ
The Itezora clan's village is on the mountain peak, right?
Now that you mention it, that does seem unnatural.
ふむ　言われてみれば不自然ではあるな
Shichika, something's been bugging me since we left Satsuma.
七花　薩摩からずっと気になっていることがあるのだが
何だ
What is it?
なぜ「ちぇすと」のことを知っておったのだ
How did you know about that "chest" expression?
I'd just heard it from my father.
いや　普通に親父から聞いてただけ
あんたがあんまりにも堂々と言うから
It's just that you were saying it so boldly that I thought maybe I was remembering wrong.
俺の記憶違いかなって思ってたんだけど
そうか
I see.
There isn't anything else you know about that you aren't telling me, is there?
ほかにはないだろうな 知っていながらわたしに黙っていること
Um...
えっと
まあ　なくはない
I guess there are...
There are?!
あるのか まったくそなたは
You're such a...
この際だ全部言っておけ
Come on, tell me all of them while we're on the topic!
O-Okay...
わ分かったよ
ええと虚刀流先代当主鑢六枝
Let's see...
I killed the previous Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Mutsue, my father, with my own hands.
つまり親父を俺はこの手で殺している
それからとがめが先の大乱の首謀者奥州の顔役俺の親父が殺した
I also know that you're the daughter of the mastermind behind the rebellion whom my father killed, Hida Takahito.
飛騨鷹比等の実の娘であることを俺は知っている
わたしの父のこと誰から聞いた
Who told you about my father?!
That ninja I fought on Fushou Island, Maniwa Koumori.
不承島で戦ったあの忍者真庭蝙蝠から
なるほどな
I see...
真庭忍軍の中でもやつとは一番付き合いがあったからな
I dealt with him more than any of the other Maniwa corps members.
The problem is, who else has Koumori told besides you?
問題はその蝙蝠がそなた以外の誰にしゃべったかだ
I think I'm the only one he told.
しゃべったのは俺にだけだと思うぜ
I think he said it to buy some time after I cornered him.
追い詰められての時間稼ぎに言ったみたいだし
その後で俺を殺すつもりだったろうから
I'm sure he intended to kill me afterwards, so I don't think it was a secret he leaked to anyone else.
秘密を漏らすつもりはなかったと思うな
I suppose...
そういえば　ほかの十二頭領と刀集めを競っておったのだったな
Come to think of it, he was competing with the other 12 heads to collect the swords.
自分が優位に立つための情報操作といったところか
I guess he withheld information from them to gain an advantage.
陰険なあの忍びらしい小ざかしさだな
That's just like him to be so impudently treacherous.
な　何だよ
W-What?
So does that mean you chose to be my sword after learning about my father?
ということは
そなたわたしの父親のことを知ってからわたしの刀になることを選んだのか
Yeah, what about it?
ああ　それが
You knew that, yet...
それを知って
いや そんなわたしだからこそ そなたはわたしにほうっ
No, because of who I was, you fell for—
とがめ
Togame?
いや いやいやいや
Nooo!
No no no no no no!
な　何すんだよ
W-What're you doing?
Sorry, I was covering up my embarrassment.
すまぬ　照れ隠しだ
That's covering embarrassment?
照れ隠し　今のが
I suppose there are no more doubts then.
そういうことならば是非もないわ
Though it doesn't change our situation.
大して状況は変わらぬということだ
No, it may even have improved it.
いや　むしろ良くなったとさえいえる
Shichika,
七花　ならばこのわたしがあらためて命令しておく
I'm going to add another order.
You must never speak of these two facts to anyone besides me.
その２つの件今後一切わたし以外の誰にも話すことを禁ずる
分かった
Understood.
Hey, Togame.
なあ　とがめ
今回無事に鎚を収集したとして
Assuming we collect Kanazuchi—
There's no assuming.
したとしてではない するのだ
We're getting it.
Yeah, I guess so.
ああ そうだったな
We collect Kanazuchi,
鎚を収集する
で残りの６本も収集して
then get the remaining 6 to complete the collection of all 12 as planned.
予定どおり１２本集めたとするよな
Right.
うむ
それからとがめはいったいどうするんだ
After that, what do you plan to do?
俺はとがめの刀として とがめの生きざまにどこまでも付き合い
As your sword, I intend to accompany you however your life turns, and stay by your side wherever you go.
どこまでも付き添うつもりだ
だけどとがめはどうなんだ
But what about you?
刀集めが終わった後
Once we finish the collection, what do you intend to do with your sword?
刀の俺をどうするつもりだ
今日ほどそなたに驚かされっ放しの日はないな
I don't think there's been a day you've surprised me more than today.
そうか
Really?
七花 虚刀流という名の刀の処遇をわたしに問うのか
Are you trying to ask me how I'm going to treat you as the Kyotouryuu sword?
わたしにとって復讐の対象となるそなたの処遇を
How I'll treat someone who should be the object of my revenge?
さて　どうしたものかな
I wonder now...
いや　とぼけておるわけではないよ
I'm not playing innocent, just so you know.
ただ考えておるのだ
I really am thinking about it.
We're still in the middle of our journey.
まだ道半ばであるし
取りあえずは四季崎記紀の変体刀集めを達成せんことには話にならんだろう
For now, we need to focus on collecting all of Shikizaki Kiki's Deviant Blades.
だからといっていいのか分からぬが
I don't know if that's a valid excuse, but it's the reason why I don't want to give an answer to your question yet.
それ故に今はまだ確定した一つの答えを持ちたくないというのが本音だ
すまぬ
Sorry.
七花
Shichika?
そなた寝ておるのか
You fell asleep?!
Honestly...
まったく そういえばわたしより先に寝るのも今日が初めてだな
Come to think of it, today is the first time you've fallen asleep before me.
Good night, Shichika.
おやすみ　七花
お待たせしました　とがめお姉ちゃん七花お兄ちゃん
Sorry to keep you waiting!
Togame Onee-chan, Shichika Onii-chan!
これが村長さんの長男が持ってた刀です
This is the sword that the mayor's eldest son owned.
That?
これが
That's not a very promising reaction...
芳しくない反応ですね
Isn't this the sword you were looking for, Togame Onee-chan?
お姉ちゃんが求めていた刀ではありませんか
Unfortunately not...
残念ながらな
That's strange...
おかしいですね
この刀と一緒にあったただし書きによれば
According to the documents that were with it, this is Kanazuchi.
これ鎚らしいですけどね
何
What?
Could you show it to me for a second?
ちょっと見せてくれないか
Okay!
いいですよ
これだ　これが鎚だ
This is it!
This is Kanazuchi!
Wait a second!
I see...
なるほど　鎚はこの世で最も重い刀なのだな
Kanazuchi is the heaviest sword ever created.
そして凍空一族とは　この世で最も力の強い一族か
And the Itezora clan's strength is unmatched by anyone else.
Even though you pride yourself on your strength, you can't even budge it.
力自慢のそなたでさえびくともしないのだから
You really have superhuman strength...
どうりでお前が怪力なわけだ
Oh no, I'm not strong at all.
いや　うちっち力持ちじゃないですよ
力比べ大会ではいっつもびりでしたからね
In the strength competitions, I always came in last place.
Of course, I could never compare with the adults,
大人とはもちろん比べものになりませんが
but I was also the weakest among the kids my age.
同い年の中でも一番か弱かったです
Weakest?!
か弱い
そうだ言い忘れましたが
Oh yeah, I forgot to mention, but according to the document, the sword can't just be given away.
ただし書きによるとこの刀簡単にあげちゃいけないものらしいです
What?
何
何どうしても欲しいっていう地表人が現れたら
If any land dweller says they really want it, they have to prove they are worthy to Kanazuchi.
この刀でもって 資格を確かめなくちゃいけないんですって
準備はいいですか 七花お兄ちゃん
Are you ready, Shichika Onii-chan?
Yeah, but it's cold.
ああ けど寒いな さっさと始めようぜ
Let's start this already,
right Togame?
なあとがめ
Yes.
うむ
いざ尋常に
Start the fight!
始めー
いっきますよぉーっ
Here I go!
Oh? You're over there, Shichika Onii-chan!
あれっ七花お兄ちゃんそこでしたか
This is kind of bothersome.
何かやりにくい
ヤベッ 斬っちゃいけないんだった
Oops, I'm not supposed to hurt her.
I have to hold back.
手加減ね 相手を傷つけずに勝つ
I must win without injuring my opponent,
or else we can't get her to carry Kanazuchi back to Owari.
じゃないとこなゆきに尾張まで鎚を運んでもらえないもんな
Kyotouryuu: Rose!
虚刀流 薔薇
Kyotouryuu
Rose
こっちですよー
I'm over here!
Now for it!
今だ
Kyotouryuu: Violet!
虚刀流 菫
Kyotouryuu Violet
ど どうだ
H-How's that?
こな ゆき
Konayuki...
面白いですね 七花お兄ちゃん
This is fun, isn't it?
Shichika Onii-chan!
I-Is it?
そ そうかよ
細かいこと考えるのをやめて
I'll stop thinking too much and try to finish this quickly in one move.
手っ取り早く奥義で決めるか
どうする
What should I do?
こなゆきの怪力に対抗するにはやはり速度
The only way I can counter Konayuki's strength is through speed, which makes Kyouka Suigetsu my only choice.
鏡花水月しかない
Shichika Onii-chan!
七花お兄ちゃん 今度はうちっちの番ですよー
It's my turn now!
What?
She can even freely change the swing of the sword?!
こなゆきは刀の軌道まで自由自在に操れるのか
Stop!
やっやめーっ
And thus in his fight with Konayuki, Yasuri Shichika suffered his first defeat on their sword collection journey.
こなゆきとの対戦で
刀集めの旅における鑢七花の戦歴に
初めて黒星が刻まれたのでございました
So that's Mt. Odori?
あれが踊山か
Doesn't seem anything special.
大したことないわねー
さーて
Now then...
どうやって料理しようかしらねー 奇策士ちゃんと虚刀流ちゃんを
how should I cook up Strategian-chan and Kyotouryuu-chan?
Everyone's looking forward to it.
みんな楽しみにしてるんだよ
I'll send them to their graves in a way that suits them best.
あいつらに一番相ふさわしい方法で葬ってやるからね
By the way, Houou...
しかし鳳凰さんよ
It's kind of sad to admit, being the leader of the Beast squad, but I still don't know much about Kyouken's ninpou.
獣組の指揮官としちゃあ情けねえかぎりなんだけど
俺 いまだに狂犬のやつの忍法がよく分かんねえんだよな
あいつとは長いんだろ
You've known her for a long time, right?
いい機会だ 教えてくれよ
This is a good opportunity, so tell me.
それは正確ではないな
That's not quite accurate.
やつが１人で一方的に長いだけだ
She is in a league by herself as far as time goes.
伝染の狂犬
"Rabid Dog the Infectious"...
It would be described as something like a "resident mind".
やつは言うならば残留思念だ
残留思念
Resident mind?
The truth is, the individual named Maniwa Kyouken died a long time ago.
実際には真庭狂犬という個人はとうの昔に死んでおるということだ
Oh, I see...
はあ なるほどね
体から体へ自由自在に移動できるってことか
She can freely jump between bodies?
ったく 便利な忍法だなー
That is one convenient ninpou...
Unfortunately, it seems there are limits to the ability.
残念ながら自由自在というわけにはゆかぬらしい
Apparently she can only target women.
移れる対象は女に限られるそうだ
ほう　それも知らなかった
I didn't know that either.
秘密の多いやつだ
Lots of secrets, that woman.
The power of Kyouken's ninpou will be beyond all description if Kanazuchi's owner turns out to be a woman.
忍法狂犬発動の恐ろしさは言葉では語り尽くせぬものがある
もし鎚の所有者が女だったら
According to Pengin-kun's information, all members of the clan are incredibly powerful.
人鳥君の情報によれば　とんでもねえ怪力一族らしいからな
Whatever the case, we must at least prevent the worst case where we lose both Kyouken and the alliance with the strategian.
いずれにしても
狂犬を失い奇策士との同盟も破れるという最悪の結果だけは
防がなければならない
だな
Right.
And for that, Kawauso...
だから川獺
It may be necessary for you to die.
もしもの場合はお主に死んでもらうことになる
Aye sir, got it.
あいさ了解
I've experienced many things as a ninja, but I've never died yet.
俺も忍びとして大概のことは経験したけど
いまだ死んだことってのはねえからよ
Now that it's come to this, I'm actually kind of looking forward to it.
こうなってくると逆に楽しみだぜ
That Koumori idiot is probably feeling lonely up there, too.
向こうで蝙蝠のバカも寂しがってるだろうしな
急ぐか
Let's hurry.
Got it.
あいよ
Shichika Onii-chan, I'm really sorry!
七花お兄ちゃん　ホントにごめんなさいです
It's fine, I said.
もういいって　気にすんな
Don't worry about it.
I never expected Shichika Onii-chan to be so weak.
まさか七花お兄ちゃんがここまで弱いなんて　うちっち思わなくって
Is my handmade jerky tasty?
うちっちの干し肉おいしいですか
Yeah.
ああ　特にウサギがたまんねえ
The rabbit one is particularly good.
Rabbit it is then!
ウサギですね
Then to help Shichika Onii-chan recover faster,
じゃあ 七花お兄ちゃんが早く治るように
I'll go hunt lots of tasty rabbits!
おいしいウサギをいっぱい捕ってきますから
Stay here and rest well.
ゆっくり休んでくださいね
Okay, thanks.
おお　ありがとな
Sorry.
ご　ごめんね
What's that all of a sudden?
何だよ　いきなり
Well, I was thinking what happened this time was maybe my fault...
その　今回のことは
やっぱりわたしの失敗だったかなとそんなふうに思っちゃって
You aren't holding a grudge against me, right?
そなたまさか根に持っているのではないだろうな
Like "a broken sword is useless",
折れた刀に使い道などないわとか
or "it's disgraceful for my sword to lose",
わたしの刀でありながら負けるとは何事だとか
or "go back to your island"?
島に帰れとか言ったことに
Or are you angry at how violent I am?
それとも暴力に訴えたことを怒っているのか
I'm not angry or bearing a grudge.
怒ってねえし　根にも持ってもいねえよ
It's true that I lost.
負けたのはホントのことだ
こなゆきが怪力だって知ってたのに
I already knew she was immensely strong, but I was underestimating her because she's a child.
子供だってことでどっかなめてたんだろうな
Though, I don't know if I could have beaten her even if I was on guard.
まあ俺に何の油断もなかったとしても
こなゆきに勝てたかどうか分からねえけど
えらく評価するのだな
You rate her abilities pretty highly even though she's just an amateur.
素人とも見えるあの少女を
Frankly, that kind of opponent is the hardest to deal with.
ぶっちゃけああいうのが一番やっかいなんだよ
The ones with no sense and logic, who are simply strong.
理屈や理論をすっ飛ばしてただ単純に強いってのが
I see.
なるほどな
You saved me with that swift decision.
とがめの判断が早くて助かったよ
If the battle had continued after that, I could have been killed.
あのまま続けてたら最悪殺されてたぜ
You'd even thank me?
そう言ってくれるか
I broke the promise...
約束破っちまったな
"Protect the swords, protect Togame, and protect myself."
刀を守れ　とがめを守れ　そして俺自身を守れ
俺は俺自身を守れなかった
I wasn't able to protect myself.
Don't be too hard on yourself.
あまり自分を責めるな
そなたを責める役は　わたしがすでにじゅうぶんやった
I've already blamed you enough.
やり過ぎた
Or maybe too much.
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい
腕の１本
Something like a fractured arm which will heal in half a month doesn't count as breaking your promise.
半月少しで回復する程度のケガなど　約束を破ったうちには入らぬよ
And I'm the one who miscalculated this time.
それに今回はわたしの失策だ
I don't intend to count it as disloyalty on your part.
そなたの不忠に数えるつもりはない
Well, thanks.
そいつはどうも
で　どうする
So, what do we do?
I still can't kill Konayuki, right?
こなゆきを殺しちゃいけないって条件は変わらないんだろう
I guess we'll be having a rematch once my left arm heals, though.
左腕が治り次第また再戦ってことになるんだろうけど
そのことだがな七花
About that, Shichika...
おそらくこなゆきとはもう戦う必要はないぞ
You probably won't have to fight Konayuki anymore.
えっどういうことだよ
What do you mean?
I'm thinking that what she said about proving we're worthy was a lie.
わたしが思うに　資格云々というのはあの子の嘘だ
A lie?
嘘
Why would she lie like that?
何でそんな嘘つくんだ
That girl is lonely.
寂しいのだよ　あの子は
When she hands over Kanazuchi, we'll leave, and she'll be all alone again.
鎚を渡せばわたしたちは帰ってしまう
そうなればまた独り
She only just lost her family to an avalanche.
雪崩で家族を失ったばかりなのだ
陽気に振る舞ってはいても
As cheerful as she's acting, I'm sure she must be longing for some company right now.
人恋しい心境になっているに違いあるまい
So she told that lie so we'd stay here longer?
だから　俺たちを引き留めるためにそんな嘘を
What a sweet lie...
カワイイ嘘であろうよ
Look!
ほら見て　これね　うちっちが仕留めたんだよ
I caught this.
I can hunt all by myself now.
うちっちもう１人で狩りができるんだよ
分かってる　嘘ついちゃいけないって
I know I shouldn't lie...
But I want to play with them...
でも遊びたかったんだもん
もう少しだけ　いいでしょ
Just a little longer, okay?
After that, I'll say sorry for lying.
そしたらきちんと嘘ついたこと謝るから
Everyone...
みんな
I'm so lonely with everyone gone...
みんながいなくて　うちっち寂しいよ
Konayuki, are you okay?!
こなゆき大丈夫か
Yes...
はい　うちっちは大丈夫です
I'm okay.
Maniwani?!
まにわに
知り合いでしたか
Is she someone you know?
I just reflexively...
知らずにこれで
Did this woman tell you her name?
この女　名乗ってはいなかったか
I think she said she's one of the 12 Maniwa Ninja Corps heads, Maniwa...
確か真庭忍軍十二頭領
まにわ　真庭狂犬とか
Maniwa Kyouken or something.
So you're Maniwa Kyouken?
お前が真庭狂犬か
十二頭領の中でも重鎮の一人に数えられる
You're a heavyweight, even among the 12 heads.
I had no idea you were a woman.
女だとは思わなかったな
Being knocked out right after showing up reminds me of Maniwa Shirasagi.
登場していきなりやられるってのは
真庭白鷺あたりを思い出すな
白鷺　蝙蝠　喰鮫　蝶々　蜜蜂　蟷螂
Shirasagi, Koumori, Kuizame, Chouchou, Mitsubachi, Kamakiri...
奇策士ちゃん　わたしの仲間をずいぶんと派手に殺してくれたわね
You've gone and brazenly killed my friends, Strategian-chan.
Thanks to you, the Maniwa Corps is a total mess!
あんたのせいで真庭忍軍はめちゃくちゃよ
So what?
だからどうした
I've watched over and protected my companions in the Maniwa village.
真庭の里の観察者として仲間を守ってきたこのわたしを
Don't take me lightly!
見くびるんじゃないわよ
I will avenge them!
仲間の敵はわたしが討つ
I'll send you to the other side with these two hands!
あんたたちをこの手であの世に送ってやる
It's nice that you're lively, but you don't look like you're in any condition to kill me.
威勢がいいのは結構だが
その様子ではわたしを殺すというのは無理そうだな
返り討ちには遭うし
You've come here just to die.
What an ill-fated woman.
まったく星の巡りの悪い女だ
Don't get too depressed, I lost to that girl too.
まあ　落ち込むなよ
その子には俺も負けちまったんだからよ
そう　それはいいことを聞いたわ
Really? How good of you to tell me.
I was uncertain whether I'd be able to defeat you with this body,
不安だったのよね　この体であんたを倒せるかどうか
since its only merit is speed.
速さだけが取り柄のこの体ではねえ
Maniwa ninpou: Kyouken Hatsudou!
真庭忍法狂犬発動
Kyouken Hatsudou
What just happened?
なっ何だ　あれ
Sorry to keep you waiting, Strategian-chan, Kyotouryuu-chan.
お待たせしたわね　奇策士ちゃん
それに虚刀流ちゃん
真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人
I am one of the 12 Maniwa corps head's, Maniwa Kyouken-chan!
真庭狂犬ちゃんよ
Amazing!
すっごい　すごいわ
Simply amazing!
力が全身に漲ってる
I can feel the power flowing through my body!
今まで乗り換えてきたどの体よりもすごいわ
This is more amazing than any other body I've taken control of before!
It's perfect!
完ぺきよ
The Itezora clan, was it?
凍空一族だっけ
It's such a shame I never knew about them before!
今まで知らなかったのが悔やまれるわ
I see, so this is how she's lived for so long...
なるほど　長年生きてきたとはこういうことか
What is this, Togame?
どういうことだよとがめ
Basically, she can jump between bodies.
つまりこやつは他人の体から体へと乗り移ることができるのだよ
She's a resident mind.
残留思念というやつだ
A resident mind!?
残留思念
意味が分かるのか
You know what that means?
いや さっぱり
Nope, not a clue.
Cheerio
Cheerio!
ちぇりお
Cheerio
とがめ　一応確認しておくけど
Togame, just making sure, but I can kill that now, right?
あれはもう殺していいんだよな
Will you be able to, Shichika?
七花　殺せるか
It'll definitely be difficult with my left arm like this,
確かにこの左腕じゃきついかもしれねえけど
そもそも万全の体調でも勝てるかどうか分からない相手なんだ
but I'm not sure if I could beat her even in top form anyway,
so it's kind of the same either way.
一緒みたいなもんだよ
I understand, Shichika.
分かった七花　殺していい
But it's not "you can kill her".
ではない　殺せ
It's "kill her".
斬り殺してやれ
Cut her down.
そうだわ　凍空の村へ行って
I know!
If I go to the Itezora village and switch to an adult woman,
大人の女に乗り換えればもっとすごいかもしれない
her body might be even more amazing!
あれ 凍空一族って全滅しちゃってんの
Oh?
The Itezora clan got wiped out?
やつは記憶も乗っ取れるのか
She even takes over memories?
ちょっと
What...
何があったっていうの
What's this memory?
What caused this devastation...
何があればこんなことに
村が凍空一族が滅ぼされて
The village... the Itezora clan was wiped out!
まあいいわ 後で川獺か人鳥に調べてもらえばすぐ分かることよね
Well, whatever.
I'll get Kawauso or Pengin to look into it later.
Hey.
おい
訳分かんねえこと言ってんじゃねえ
Stop spouting garbage.
You came here to kill me, didn't you?
俺を殺しに来たんだろうが
I'll play with you, Maniwa Kyouken.
相手してやるよ 真庭狂犬
そうだったわね 虚刀流
That's correct, Kyotouryuu.
白鷺 蝙蝠 喰鮫 蝶々 蜜蜂 蟷螂
Shirasagi, Koumori, Kuizame, Chouchou, Mitsubachi, Kamakiri.
あんたたちの敵をそっちに送ってやるからね
I'll be sending your enemies over to you soon.
肉はみんなで分けて食べな
Make sure you share them out when you eat them!
この動きもしかして
Are those movements...
Let me tell you something interesting, Kyotouryuu-chan.
いいこと教えてあげようか虚刀流ちゃん
わたしは記憶を乗っ取れるだけじゃない
I don't just take over memories.
I inherit them.
記憶を引き継げるのよ
I've taken over more than 2000 bodies in my lifetime.
これまでわたしが乗っ取ってきた肉体の数は千や二千じゃきかない
そのほとんどが武芸に秀でた女武者だった
Most of them were female ninja, highly skilled in the martial arts.
I don't know how many years of experience you have, but I have several thousand times more!
あんたが何年修行してきたか知らないけど
わたしにはその何千倍もの経験がある
All I've got is 20 years of training, and I haven't even done real battle 20 times.
どうせ俺の修行期間はたかが２０年だよ
実戦経験だって２０回もねえ
待てよ
Wait, if it's like this, maybe I should check to see.
こうなったら 確かめるか
何よ逃げの一手
What, you're trying to escape?
How pathetic. Is that how a swordsman acts?
みっともないわね それでも剣士のつもり
No, I just wanted to confirm something.
いやちょっとばかし気になることがあってさ
一応確認
はあ 確認
What? Confirm?
てめえの死体でも確認してろ このでくのぼうが
Why don't you go confirm your corpse!
Stupid blockhead!
Kyotouryuu: Plum!
虚刀流 梅
Kyotouryuu
Plum
決まった
It landed!
どういうことだ 七花
How did you do that, Shichika?
I don't know why, but ever since Konayuki was taken over, I've been able to read her movements clearly.
何でか分からないけど
こいつがこなゆきに乗り移った途端
動きがはっきりと見えるようになったんだよ
I see...
そうか
You couldn't read Konayuki's movements since she was a complete amateur, but Kyouken is an experienced assassin.
こなゆきはど素人だったが 故に読めなかったが
狂犬は熟練された忍び
And on top of that, she has the combined experience of thousands of people.
おまけに何千人もの経験が詰め込まれている
It makes sense that you can read her movements now.
となればそなたに相手の手が読めないわけがない
七花 命令だ
Shichika, this is an order.
その女がわたしの体を乗っ取ったら ちゅうちょなくわたしを殺せ
If that woman takes over my body, kill me without hesitation.
As brutally as you can.
それもできる限り無残にだ
Understood.
了解
わたしの刀相手に人質が通じるなどと思うなよ
Don't think for a moment that a hostage strategy would work against my sword.
ちなみにわたしの強度は障子紙並みだ
Just so you know, the strength of my body is on par with sliding door paper.
つまずいて転んだだけでも死ぬ自信がある
I'm confident I can die just by falling over.
ウサギに襲われても負ける自信がある
I'm also confident that I can lose in a fight with a rabbit.
それでも乗っ取りたければこの体いくらでも乗っ取れ
If you still want to take over my body despite that, go ahead.
However, by that point you'll be torn into pieces.
ただしそのころにはあんたは八つ裂きになってるだろうけどな
真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人 真庭狂犬
I am one of the 12 Maniwa Ninja Corps heads, Maniwa Kyouken!
仲間の敵だ これでも食らいな
I will avenge my friends!
Now...
Eat this!
なるほど
I get it now.
あれが双刀という名のゆえんか
That's why that sword is called "pair".
There's no clear handle or tip, so you're free to hold it either way.
上下の区別があいまいな故どちらでもない自在を意味する
双刀之犬
Soutounoinu!
Soutounoinu
虚刀流 飛花落葉
Kyotouryuu: Hikara Kuyou!
Kyotouryuu Hikara Kuyou
入れ墨が 真庭狂犬の入れ墨が消えてゆくぞ
The tattoo...
Maniwa Kyouken's tattoo is vanishing!
七花 これは
Shichika, what did you...
ひょっとして入れ墨だけを攻撃したら
I thought maybe if I only attacked the tattoo, I could defeat Kyouken without killing Konayuki.
こなゆきを殺さなくても狂犬を倒せるんじゃないかと思って
It looks like it worked.
うまくいったみたいだ
That's a relief.
よかったぜ
We have to get Konayuki to carry Kanazuchi to Owari, right?
こなゆきには鎚を尾張まで運んでもらわなくちゃならないんだろ
Y-Yeah...
あああ そのとおりだ 見事だ 七花
That's right.
Well done, Shichika.
初めて七花が自分の判断で斬らなかった
This is the first time Shichika made his own decision not to kill his opponent.
And against my orders, too.
わたしの命令に逆らって
一本の日本刀としての虚刀流
Kyotouryuu is but a single sword,
しかし虚刀流である以前に人間でもある
but before that, he's also a human.
わたしは七花にそれを自覚させようと思っていた
I thought I should wake up that human side in Shichika,
刀としてではなく 人として
to make him find his resolve as a person, not as a sword.
彼に覚悟を決めさせようと
そうでなければ 乗り越えられない局面があるはずだと
I told myself there would be insurmountable hurdles if I didn't.
だが実際こうなってみるとどうだろう
But now that it's actually happened, was I right?
この２カ月でわたしがやったことは
Maybe everything I've done in the last two months has merely served to dull his blade.
いたずらに刀の斬れ味を落としただけではないのか
All because, as his owner, I didn't know how to handle this sword.
ただ刀の所有者として 刀を扱いきれないというだけの理由で
ちぇりお
Cheerio.
It seems we're too late.
遅きに失したようだな
真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人 真庭鳳凰
I'm one of the 12 Maniwa Ninja Corps heads, Maniwa Houou.
Likewise, I'm one of the 12 Maniwa Ninja Corps heads, Maniwa Kawauso.
同じくひとしく真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人 真庭川獺だよん
貴様らよくもぬけぬけと わたしの前に顔を出せたものだな
You have some nerve to show your faces in front of me!
Don't glare like that, Togame-chan.
そうにらむなよ とがめちゃん
一緒に悪さした仲じゃねえか
We used to work together in the shadows, didn't we?
Shut up!
ほざけ
結局は最悪の場合に至ったということだな
It would appear the worst case happened after all.
Right.
だな
And now Strategian-dono has lost her trust in us.
そして 奇策士殿のわれらへの信頼も失墜したというわけだ
I put no trust in you people from the start!
貴様らに信頼など最初からない
早合点しないでくれ われと川獺は狂犬を止めに来たのだ
Please don't jump to conclusions.
Kawauso and I came here to stop Kyouken.
今回のことは狂犬の独断専行
Kyouken moved of her own accord this time.
I wouldn't want you to think that the Maniwa Corps agreed to this.
決して真庭忍軍の相違であると思わないでほしい
しかし
However, it's entirely understandable if you wish to break up the alliance after this incident.
奇策士殿がわれらとの同盟を破棄したいと思ってもそれは無理からぬこと
The alliance is already over.
同盟はすでに破綻しておる
Don't say that...
そう言うな
We were definitely in the wrong this time, so please allow us to take responsibility.
今回のことはわれの不徳の致すところだ
どうか責任を取らせてはもらえないだろうか
Responsibility?
責任
川獺
Kawauso.
Alrighty.
はいな
とがめちゃんよ あんた俺の忍法を知ってるよな
Togame-chan, you know what my ninpou is, right?
真庭忍法 記録辿りを
Maniwa ninpou: Record Tracer.
記録辿り
Record Tracer?
狂犬がこなゆきの記憶を探っていたであろう
Kyouken was searching through Konayuki's memories, remember?
川獺はそれを生命ならぬ物体においてできるのだ
Kawauso can do the same thing with inanimate objects.
まあ簡単に言えば いわゆる探魂法だ
Basically, it's a form of psychometry.
探魂法
Psycho me tree?
Objects have spirits, same as people, Kyotouryuu.
物にも人と同じで心があるってやつだよ 虚刀流
まあ 全部が全部読めるってわけじゃないし
Though it doesn't mean I can read absolutely anything, and conversely to Kyouken, I can't read people's memories.
狂犬とは別に俺は人の心は読めないんだけどな
内気なもんで
I'm too shy for that.
If you can do that...
そんなことができたら
そなたでも分かるか
So you understand now how useful this man's ninpou is for sword gathering.
この男の忍法が刀集めのようなうせ物捜しにおいて
どれほど有効な忍法なのか
That's quite the secret weapon they kept hidden.
とんでもねえ秘密兵器隠してたんだな
Right?
だな
で 責任とは何なのだ
So, what do you mean by responsibility?
さっさと言え
Hurry up and tell us.
Right.
おわびに川獺の忍法を貸すと言っても
Even if I offered to lend you Kawauso's ability, you wouldn't trust us.
お主らは忍びの言うことなど信じないだろう
And so I have no choice but to do this.
だから こうするしかないのだ
これで 真庭忍軍十二頭領はわれを含めて残り４人となった
With this, the 12 heads of the Maniwa Corps, including myself, are down to 4.
これならばお主にとって われらはさほど恐るべき敵とはいえまい
At this point, I'm sure you agree we cannot pose any real threat to you,
細かな同盟規約違反など優しく見逃してやってくれまいか
so could you overlook this minor violation of our alliance?
You...
貴様それでも一軍の統率者か
You call yourself a leader?
I told you before, you're overstating things.
だからそれは買いかぶりだと言っている
真庭忍軍に統率者はいらない
The Maniwa Corps needs no leader.
Shinobi merely live and die.
忍びは生きて死ぬだけだ
How about it then?
どうする
川獺の探魂法を失ったわれらにもなお
If you still insist that we're a threat to you even without Kawauso's psychometry, then there's no choice.
奇策士殿が恐れをなすと言うのならばやむを得まい
ここでわれらはお主らの相手となろう
I will have to fight you here.
われにも仲間の敵を討ちたいという気持ちはあるのだから
I, too, harbor the urge to avenge my companions—
I'll let it pass!
見逃してやる
I'll ignore this incident.
今回のことは不問に付す
だからさっさとわたしの視界から姿を消せ
Hurry up and get out of my sight!
I don't want to see that unpleasant grin of yours any longer!
その不愉快な笑みをこれ以上わたしに見せるな
I thank you for your generous treatment.
寛大な処置に この真庭鳳凰痛み入る
そうそう この間お主に伝えた情報だが
Ah, yes...
About what I told you the last time...
Apparently the owner of Shireizan's sword changed a few days ago.
死霊山にあった刀の所有者がつい先日変わったらしい
所有者が変わった
Its owner changed?
われらやお主ら以外にも刀集めをしている者が存在するということだ
It means that there's someone besides yourselves and us gathering the swords.
新しい所有者は陸奥から四国行きの船に乗ったそうだぞ
It would seem that the new owner got on a boat from Roku to Shikoku.
四国
Shikoku...
早めに対応しておくことを勧める
I recommend you deal with it soon.
何せあの死霊山を
The new owner is a monster that laid waste to Shireizan in a mere half hour.
わずか半時で壊滅に追い込んだほどの化け物らしいからな
I'm sorry I lied to you.
嘘ついてごめんなさいでした
もうよい
It's okay.
All that aside, we're counting on you.
それより頼んだぞ そなたにしかできぬことだ
You're the only one who can do this.
Leave it to me!
任してください
I'll be sure to take it to Owari.
うちっちちゃんと尾張まで運びますから
Yup.
おう頑張れよ
Do your best.
それとそなたがこれから住まう三途神社のことだが
And don't worry about the Sanzu shrine where you'll be living from now on.
案ずることはない
そなたの先祖も出雲の出らしいからな
I've heard that your ancestors originally came from Izumo.
これも何かの縁であろうはい
I'm sure this is fate.
Okay!
はい
とがめお姉ちゃん　七花お兄ちゃん
Togame Onee-chan, Shichika Onii-chan!
いっぱい遊んでくれてありがとう
Thanks for playing with me!
うちっちとっても楽しかったです
It was really fun.
We're finally heading to Shikoku, Shichika.
いよいよ四国だぞ　七花
そなたが見たがっていた刀大仏が見られる
We can go see the giant Sword Buddha statue that you wanted to see.
Yeah...
どうした　元気ないな
What's wrong?
You look down.
何つーか心残りが
How to put it... I feel some regret.
何心変わり
What?
A change of heart?
そなた少女趣味だったのか　わたしよりもあんな小娘の方がよいと
I didn't know you had a thing for little girls!
Are you telling me you prefer that young girl over m—
No no, I said regrets, not a change of heart.
いやいや 心残り
心変わりじゃなくて
ほら狂犬には勝てたけど 結局こなゆきには負けたままだろ
We managed to defeat Kyouken, but my defeat by Konayuki still stands.
なまじ狂犬に勝っちゃったせいか心残りが
That's why I still feel regret after beating Kyouken.
ああ それはわたしが何度も説明してやったろう
I see. I already explained that to you.
Konayuki's hit was just an amateur fluke that happened to catch you.
あれはこなゆきが素人であるが故にたまたま入ってしまっただけの一撃だ
気に病むことはない
It's nothing to worry about.
本来ならば負けのうちにも入らぬよ
That wouldn't normally even count as a loss.
そういうもんかね
Really?
No matter how many times you say it, I don't get it.
何度聞いても分かんねえや
Are you sure you haven't had a change of heart?
むまさか本当に心変わりしたのではないだろうな
Do you want me to wrap my hair around you again?
久しぶりにこの髪巻いてみない
A change of heart is impossible.
心変わりなんてあり得ないよ
I'm your sword, after all.
俺はとがめの刀なんだ
それならばよいのだが
Well, that's fine then.
頼むぞ まったくま
Don't make me worry like that.
あどうしてもこなゆきと決着をつけたいと言うのならば
Well, if you absolutely must conclude your fight with her, do it after finishing our sword collection journey.
刀集めの旅を終えてからのことにしてくれよ
Okay.
了解だ とがめ
Understood, Togame.
七花の人間性は刀集めの旅のさなか順調に育ちつつあったのでございます
Shichika's humanity was making fast progress as they reached the midpoint of their sword collection journey.
翌月の決戦の地は
Next month's deciding battle will take place in the holiest ground for swordsmen, Mt. Sayabashiri,
剣士にとって最大の聖地
土佐は鞘走山 刀大仏の鎮座する清涼院護険寺
inside the Seiryouingoken temple where the Buddha of swords sits.
校倉必凍空こなゆきと
Shichika has achieved victory without killing the owner twice in succession now with Azekura Kanara and Itezora Konayuki,
所有者を殺さない勝ち方を２度続けて経験した七花は
その対決において姉殺しを経験するのでございます
but in his next fight, he will undergo the experience of killing his own sister.
刀か心 あるいは その両方ともが折られるのか
Will the sword, the heart, or both of them be broken?
今月こよいの『刀語』 お楽しみはここまでにございます
The story of Katanagatari on this month and this evening ends here.
粉雪を凝らせようか
konayuki wo koorase you ka
I wonder if I should freeze the snow
死に間うまれに吐き息ひとつだ
chi ni mau mae ni
before it drifts down to the ground
haku iki hitotsu de
with a single breath
つららと見紛う　氷の匕首
tsurara to mimagou koori no aikuchi
The dagger of ice, mistaken for an icicle
雲が裂ける旅に　月も刃を見せよ
kumo ga sakebu tabi ni
Each time a cloud yells
tsuki mo ha wo mise you
the moon will show the blade
憎しみのために　出会う私語の
nikushimi no tame ni (deau sadame mo)
Even a fate I encounter (because of hate)
まだ愛し故に　愛より青く
mata itoshii yue ni (ai yori aoku)
Also for love (bluer than indigo)
omoi wo togeru sono hi niwa
On the day when I realize my wish
思いを遂げるその日には
shizuke ni sora wa sumiyuki
the sky will quietly be perfectly clear
静かに　空は澄みゆき
遂げるだろう
tokeru darou
and fate will melt into the sky
七花のやつ　別の女に心残りを覚えるとは生意気な
To think that Shichika would feel regret over another woman...
今夜は髪の毛でギュウギュウにして私を忘れないようにしてやる
I'll wrap him up with my hair so tight he won't forget me!
Now then, the owner of the sword for next episode...
さて　次の刀の持ち主だが
まさか彼女が立ち塞がることになるとはな
To think she of all people would stand in our path...
鑢七実　何を考えている
What is Yasuri Nanami thinking?
Next time on Katanagatari: Akutou Bita.
次回　刀語　悪刀　鐚
今見せる　七花の新必殺技
We'll show you Shichika's new ultimate move!
まあ　それはこれから考えるものだがな
Well, I'm thinking it up now...
Akutou
Bita
Poor,
the Evil
ちぇりお
Cheerio!